# Vikash Goyal

Senior Data Scientist, 7+ Years' Experience

Email: vikashgoyal2701@gmail.com LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/vikash-goyal Phone: +91-9760173419

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

**Data Science lead** at Citi with **7+** years of experience in business decision making by using **Machine learning, Deep learning algorithms** & **Artificial Intelligence**. Currently leading projects in **Customer Experience** vertical. Responsible for requirement gathering, development & delivery of end-to-end solutions. Industry exposure in **Banking, Retail, Healthcare** etc.

### **EXPERIENCE**

CITI | LEAD DATA SCIENTIST

February 2020 - Current | Bangalore, India

- → Developed an Early warning detection system to predict hidden attrition from institutional clients
  - Hidden attrition reduces **40%** of revenue growth. Designed a multi-dimensional framework to prioritise customers with high attrition risk and low regulatory risk
  - Worked in a cross-functional role with different product & risk teams to leverage datasets like Transactions, Balances, Pricing, VOC surveys, Call reports & Deals.
  - Trained (XGBoost model giving an accuracy of 82%(covering 292 clients from 356 clients provided by C@R) and captured \$140 Mn at risk
- → Developed a Shell Company Account identification model using Network Analysis
  - Worked with business, vendors & ingestion team to expose third party vendor data
  - Used Community Detection Algorithm to isolate suspicious accounts. Trained Isolation Forest model using features from transaction feed & company profile to detect anomalies.
  - Model is working at 76% accuracy in detecting potential shell accounts. Led to 3
     FTE reduction from AML research team
- → Automated the transaction monitoring process which generates insights for **KYC** renewal of accounts. As a part of that, developed a stacked classifier to tag an entity name as Individual/Corporation using **CNN-1D & GBM**. Accuracy achieved is **96%** and rolled out this algorithm to enhance payments data for **CITI wide consumption**

#### **EXL SERVICES** | DATA SCIENTIST

April 2017 - January 2020 | Gurugram, India

- → Developed an NLP fraud detection model to identify fraud in text based legal invoices. Features from text data was extracted using techniques like tf-idf, topic modelling, k-means clustering, Word Embedding etc. and XGBoost was used to build the final classifier. Captured 82% of frauds in the top 2 deciles which accounted to \$3+ Mn potential adjustments after analysing \$40+ Mn legal spends
- → Developed a binary classifier to predict cricket WC'19 matches for the EXL Hackathon. Built a **web scraper** to extract information around matches, player statistics, ranking etc. from Internet. Various features like **player's historical stats, recent form, pitch impact** etc. were created to train a **Random Forest** model. Achieved an **accuracy of 78%** and secured **4th** rank across EXL

### **AXTRIA INDIA PVT.LTD.** | BUSINESS ANALYST

June 2016 - March 2017 | Gurgaon, India

→ Automated the process used for weekly sales tracking of an Oncology brand. Worked on multiple Ad-hoc analysis to generate insights for a major healthcare firm

### **EDUCATION**

# INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (IIT), ROORKEE

B.Tech in Production & Industrial Engineering
July 2012 - June 2016
CGPA: 7.7

### SKILLS

### **PROGRAMMING**

- Python
- Pyspark
- Pytorch
- SQL

### **CORE COMPETENCIES**

• Logistic Regression • Random Forest • KNN • GBM • XGBoost • K-Means • Machine Learning • Deep Learning • NLP • Large Language Models LLM • GCP • Topic Modelling • Word Embeddings • Network Analysis • Neural Networks • Isolation Forest • DBSCAN • Hypothesis testing • A/B Testing • Attrition Prediction • AML & Compliance • Fraud Detection

# **ACCOMPLISHMENTS**

- Trained 100+ campus hires in Python, Pyspark & ML
- Recognitions: Platinum Award & Delivery Excellence Award(2022), Silver Award (2021), Copper Award (2020) by AIM Bangalore, Citi
- Cleared CFA level 1 in Jan'18 and CFA level 2 in Aug'18